Guide to the Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre Records, 1997-2015 CTC.2009.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre Records
1997-2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre
CTC.2009.02
10 Linear Feet (22 document boxes)
The Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre, now PICT Classic Theatre, is a performing arts company which began in 1997. PICT is one of Pittsburgh's larger professional theatre companies and focuses on producing Irish, English, and classical plays along with related new works. This collection contains video recordings of the group's productions, photographs, programs, board meeting minutes, and some marketing materials.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stephanie Riso in August 2009. Additional materials were donated in June 2015.
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre records primarily consist of video recordings of the PICT's theatre productions. There is a recording for nearly every PICT production from its inception in 1997 through 2014. These recordings have been made available in agreement with Actors' Equity Association. Along with the recording, each production's files may also include related materials - newspaper clippings, programs, photographs, promotional materials, etc. There are also two other series in the collection containing organizational files and posters.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre Records, 1997-2015, CTC.2009.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The records are organized into three series.
Series I. Productions, 1997-2014
Series II. Organizational and Marketing Files, 1997-2008
Series III. Posters, 1998-2015
Access Restrictions
No restrictions, but please note that the video recordings in this collection must be used according to the guidelines set by the Actors' Equity Association. Researchers must contact the staff of the Special Collections Department in advance and make a request to view a recording. About half of the recordings cannot be viewed until the library has a user copy made from the original master recording donated by the Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre. Recordings without user copies are noted as such in the production's scope note.
History
Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre (PICT) was founded in 1996 by Andrew S. Paul and Stephanie Riso. PICT's mission is to produce innovative interpretations of dramatic literature in the classic and Irish traditions. Since its inception, PICT has grown to be one of the larger professional theatre companies in Pittsburgh. Alan Stanford became the artistic director of the company in 2013. As of 2015, PICT has produced eighty-nine main stage shows, including six world premieres, eight U.S. premieres, and forty Pittsburgh premieres. In addition to the great works of Shakespeare, Shaw, and Wilde, and their contemporaries, PICT has familiarized Pittsburgh audiences with modern Irish and British playwrights including Brian Friel, Thomas Kilroy, Martin McDonagh, Tom Stoppard, Conor McPherson, David Hare, Harold Pinter, and Marina Carr. Between 2003-2015, most PICT productions have been performed at the theatres in the Stephen Foster Memorial building in Oakland on the University of Pittsburgh campus.
There have been seven actors of PICT productions to be named the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette Performer of the Year - Simon Bradbury, Derdriu Ring, Martin Giles, Scott Ferrara, Sheila McKenna, Douglas Rees, and David Whalen. Many of the PICT's productions have been named as among the very best in several local publication's year-end lists.
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 -- Stage history -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Art and popular culture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre; Paul, Andrew S.; Riso, Stephanie; Stanford, Alan
- Productions, 1997-2014; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Within this series are the production files of the Pittsburgh Irish & Classical Theatre. Each annual season is treated as a subseries and each production in the season is treated as a section. Most production's files include newspaper clippings, programs, photographs, promotional materials, and a video recording. Video formats include VHS cassettes, DVD discs, and digital video cassettes. All photographs after 2005 are black and white images printed on non-photographic paper. The production of King Lear in 2008 is the most well documented production in the collection. In addition to the normal array of materials it includes performance reports, production meeting reports, rehearsal reports, and set designs.
  - 1997 Season, 1.
    - The Constant Couple, 1997
      The Constant Couple, written by George Farquhar, was PICT's first production. It was directed by Andrew S. Paul and performed at Duquesne University during June 1997. Photographs by George Mendel. Video production by R.L.G. Creations.
      - Newspaper clippings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Photographs, May 5, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1998 Season, 2.
    - Translations, April 1998
      The play Translations was written by Brian Friel, and directed by Holly Thuma. It was performed April 23 - May 10, 1998, at the Lester Hamburg Studio Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Christian Rummel and Stephanie Riso. Photographs by George Mendel. Randy Griffith was the videographer.
      Please note that the recording of this production cannot be viewed until a user copy is created.
      - Newspaper clippings, April 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Photographs, April 2, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Program (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Video recording, 1 video VHS master (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Too Clever By Half, June 1998
      The play Too Clever by Half was written by Alexander Ostrovsky, with the English language version by Rodney Ackland. It was directed by Dan Kamin, and performed June 17-18, 1998, on City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the production include Allan Pinsker, Shirley Tannenbaum, and Ben Tatar. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, June 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Program (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The White Devil, September 1998
      The play The White Devil was written by John Webster, and adapted by Daniel Frezza and Andrew S. Paul. It was directed by Andrew S. Paul and ran September 10-27, 1998, at the Pittsburgh Playhouse. AEA members involved in the production include Christian Rummel and Christopher Josephs. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, September 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1999 Season, 3.
    - Juno and the Paycock, April 1999
      Juno and the Paycock was written by Sean O'Casey, and directed by Hal O'Leary in a run from April 22-May 9, 1999, in the Lester Hamburg Studio Theatre. AEA members include Stephanie Riso, David L. Doepken, and Ginger Auld. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, April 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Program (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Rivals, 1999
      The play The Rivals by Richard Brinsley Sheridan was directed by Dan Kamin. It ran June 2-13, 1999, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the production include David Crawford, Tom Langdon, Tim Hartman, and Barbara Russell. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Video recording, 3 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Racing Demon, August 1999
      The play Racing Demon was written by David Hare, and directed by Lora Oxenreiter in a run from August 19-September 5, 1999, in Lester Hamburg Studio Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Amy Lammert, David Crawford, and Tom Langdon. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, August 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Program (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Video recording, 3 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 2000 Season, 4.
    - Faith Healer, 2000
      The play Faith Healer was written by Brian Friel, and directed by Andrew S. Paul, in a run from March 23-April 8, 2000, at the Lester Hamburg Studio Theatre. AEA Members involved in the performance include Bingo O'Malley and Kate Young. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The Cripple of Inishman, June 2000
      The Cripple of Inishmaan was written by Martin McDonagh and directed by Timothy Douglas, in a run from June 8-24, 2000, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the performance include Kate Young, Larry John Meyers, and Derdriu Ring. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, June 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Program (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Henceforward, July 2000
      The play Henceforward was written by Alan Ayckbourn, and directed by Dan Kamin, in a run from July 14-29, 2000, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members include Cary Anne Spear, Ronald H. Siebert, David Crawford, and Joe Schulz. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, July 2000 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Program (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Video recording, 1 disc DVD user copy (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Video recording, July 2000; 1 video VHS master (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - The Picture of Dorian Gray, August 2000
      The Picture of Dorian Gray was adapted from Oscar Wilde's novel by Daniel Frezza. It was directed by W. Stephen Coleman and ran from August 10-26, 2000 at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the production include W. Stephen Coleman, Ken Bolden, Doug Mertz, Robin Walsh, E. Bruce Hill, and Hillary Cook. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, August 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 2001 Season, 5.
    - Portia Coughlan, March 2001
      The play Portia Coughlan was written by Marina Carr, and directed by Timothy Douglas, in a run from March 22-April 7, 2001, at the Eddy Theatre, Chatham College. AEA members involved include Derdriu Ring, Douglas Rees, Alex Coleman, Kate Young, E. Bruce Hill, Ginger Lawrence, Catherine Moore, Christian Rummel, and Kelly Yann. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, March 2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Program (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Tartuffe, June 2001
      The play Tartuffe was written by Moliere, and translated by Christopher Hampton. It was directed by Jonathan Rest in a run from June 14-30, 2001, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the performance include Ginger Lawrence, Alex Coleman, Kate Young, Andrew S. Paul, Leah Akins, Gene Saraceni, Roger Jerome, Robin Walsh, and Laura R. Fincke. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, June 2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Program (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Tonight @ 8:30, July 2001
      The play Tonight at 8:30 was written by Noel Coward and directed by Dan Kamin, in a run from July 12-28, 2001, at City Theatre Mainstage. The play consists of three shorter works, titled Ways and Means, Fumed Oak, and Shadow Play. AEA members involved in the performance include Doug Mertz, Kate Young, Martin Giles, Catherine Moore, amd Michael Fuller. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, July 2001 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Program (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - The Seagull, August 2001
      The play The Seagull was written by Thomas Kilroy, after Chekhov. It was directed by Andrew S. Paul and was performed from August 9-25, 2001, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the performance include Martin Giles, Alex Coleman, Catherine Moore, Helena Ruoti, Jarrod Fry, and Jessie Ksanznak. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, August 2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Program (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS master and user copy (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 2002 Season, 6.
    - The Gigli Concert, 2002
      The play The Gigli Concert was written by Tom Murphy, and directed by Andrew S. Paul, in a run from May 30-June 15, 2002, at the Lester Hamburg Studio Theatre. AEA members involved include Martin Giles, Larry John Meyers, Caitlin Clarke, and Jessie Ksanznak.
      - Newspaper clippings, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Video recording, 2 videos VHS user copy (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Storytellers
      Part of PICT's 2002 season was a Sunday night play readings program. The following plays were a part of that program - Samuel Beckett's First Love on June 9-10, David Hare's Via Dolorosa on July 21, Conor McPherson's St. Nicholas on August 18.
      - Promotional materials (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - She Stoops to Conquer, July 2002
      The play She Stoops to Conquer was written by Oliver Goldsmith, and directed by Melanie Dreyer, in a run from July 11-27, 2002, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the production include Joe Warik, Roger Jerome, Michael Fuller, E. Bruce Hill, Barbara Russell, Colleen Delany, and Jessie Ksanznak. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, July 2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Program (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Video recording, July 25, 2002; 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Video recording, July 25, 2002; 2 videos VHS user copy (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Aristocrats, August 2002
      The play Aristocrats was written by Brian Friel and directed by Andrew S. Paul in a run from August 8-24, 2002, at City Theatre Mainstage. AEA members involved in the production include James Critchfield, Larry John Meyers, Joe Schulz, Colleen Delany, and Caitlin Clark.
      - Newspaper clippings, August 2002 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Program (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Video recording, 1 video Digital video cassette master (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Video recording, 1 video VHS user copy (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Faith Healer - Ireland tour, 2002
      Faith Healer was performed in 13 cities in Ireland during October and November, 2002. This was PICT's first international tour. In advance of the tour, the play was also performed on October 8th, 2002 at Pittsburgh's Byham Theater.
      - Newspaper clippings, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Program (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Promotional materials (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 2003 Season, 7.
    - Hamlet, May 2003
      The play Hamlet was written by William Shakespeare, and directed by Andrew S. Paul, in a run from May 8-24, 2003, at the Charity Randall Theatre in the Stephen Foster Memorial. AEA members involved in the production include Doug Pona, Christian Rummel, Martin Giles, Helena Ruoti, Scott Ferrara, Gene A. Saraceni, Elena Alexandratos, and Jessie Ksanznak. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Education flyer (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Newspaper clippings, May 2003 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Program (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Video recording, 2 video Digital video cassette master (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Major Barbara, 2003
      The play Major Barbara was written by George Bernard Shaw and directed by Matt O'Brien, in a run from June 12-28, 2003, at the Charity Randall Theatre in the Stephen Foster Memorial. The play was revived later in the same year. AEA members involved in the production include Kate Young, Derdriu Ring, Scott Ferrara, Andrew S. Paul, E. Bruce Hill, Bingo O'Malley, Ingrid Sonnichsen, and Jessie Ksanznak. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Program (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Video recordings, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Video recordings, 2 videos VHS user copy (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Copenhagen, 2003
      The play Copenhagen was written by Michael Frayne and directed by Gregory Lehane in a run from July 10 - August 2 and November 7 - 23, 2003, in the Henry Heymann Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Larry John Meyers and Darren Eliker.
      - Newspaper clippings, July 2003 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 2004 Season, 8.
    - A Woman of No Importance, 2004
      The play A Woman of No Importance was written by Oscar Wilde, and directed by Andrew S. Paul, in a run from April 29-May 15, 2004, at the Charity Randall Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Susan McGregor-Laine, Helena Ruoti, Melanie Dreyer, Martin Giles, John Shepard, Ben Tatar, Laurie Klatscher, and E. Bruce Hill. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Education flyer (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Newspaper clippings, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Program (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Travesties, June 2004
      The play Travesties was written by Tom Stoppard, and directed by Gregory Lehane, in a run from June 3-19, 2004, at the Charity Randall Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Douglas Rees, Greg Logenhagen, Martin Giles, Larry John Meyers, Jessica Bates, Heath Lamberts, and Sheila McKenna. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, June 2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Program (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Stones in His Pockets, July 2004
      The play Stones in His Pockets was written by Marie Jones, and directed by Stuart Carden, in a run from July 8-August 1, 2004, at the Henry Heymann Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Jay O'Berski, Joe Schulz, Phill Madore.
      - Newspaper clippings, July 2004 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Program (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Video recording, 1 video Digital video cassette master (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Uncle Vanya, August 2004
      The play Uncle Vanya was written by Anton Chekhov, and this adaptation is by Brian Friel. It was directed by Andrew S. Paul in a run from August 12-September 4, 2004, at the Henry Heymann Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Larry John Meyers, Kate Eastwood Norris, Ginger Lawrence, Martin Giles, Heath Lamberts, Susan McGregor-Laine, and Alicia DeMara. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Newspaper clippings, August 2004 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Photographs (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Dead, December 2004
      The Dead is a musical adaptation of a short story in James Joyce's Dubliners. The book was written by Richard Nelson, with music by Shaun Davey. It was directed by Scott Wise, and ran December 2-18, 2004, at the Charity Randall Theatre. AEA members involved in the production include Paul Todaro, Stephanie Riso, Joel Ripka, Rosaleen Linehan, Scott J. Pearson, Ingrid Sonnichsen, Daina Michelle Griffith, David Cabot, Derdriu Ring, Kate Young, Larry John Meyers, and Barbara A. Slavin. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Education flyer (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Newspaper clippings, December 2004 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Photographs (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Program (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Video recording, 1 video Digital video cassette master (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Video recording, 1 video VHS user copy (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Video recording, 1 disc DVD user copy (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - 2005 Season, 9.
    - Chaplin, February 2005
      The play Chaplin was written by Simon Bradbury. It was directed by Neil Munro and performed by Simon Bradbury, who is a member of AEA. It was performed from February 17-March 12, 2005, at the Henry Heymann Theatre.
      - Newspaper clippings, February 2005 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Photographs (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Program (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Henry IV, April 2005
      The play Henry IV was written by William Shakespeare and adapted by Dakin Matthews. It was directed by Andrew S. Paul in a run from April 20-May 14, 2005, at the Charity Randall Theatre. AEA members involved in the performance include Brian Barefoot, Alex Coleman, David Conrad, David Crawford, Scott Ferrara, Martin Giles, Tim Hartman, E. Bruce Hill, Sheila McKenna, Kate Eastwood Norris, Sam Tsoutsouvas, and Alicia DeMara. Photographs by Suellen Fitzsimmons.
      - Education flyer (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Newspaper clippings, April 2005 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Photographs (Box 10, Folder 20)
      - Program (Box 10, Folder 21)
      - Promotional postcard (Box 10, Folder 22)
      - Video recording, 2 videos Digital video cassette master (Box 10, Folder 23)
      - Video recording, 2 discs DVD user copy (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Heartbreak House, June 2005
      The play Heartbreak House was written by George Bernard Shaw, and was directed by Gregory Lehane during June 2-25, 2005, at the Charity Randall Theatre. AEA members involved in the performance include Caitlin Muelder, Susan McGregor-Laine, Sam Tsoutsouvas, Laurie Klatscher, Helena Ruoti, Robert Haley, Tom Schaller, Larry John Meyers, Scott Ferrara, E. Bruce Hill, and Alicia DeMara.